howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show this is a current episode
currents are shorter and less heavily
produced than our full-length episodes
and generally focus on a single topic as
always links to books articles and
organizations mentioned are available on
the episode page at Jim read show calm
that's Jim rut show calm today's guests
on this current episode is Joe Norman
Joe is a complexity science researcher a
data scientist and a homesteader in
Western Massachusetts that right north
of New Hampshire I'm in southwestern New
Hampshire very close to Western Maine
okay southwestern New Hampshire I've
been there it's probably a is it near
Mount Monadnock by any chance
we're in the Monadnock Region that's
exactly right yeah when I was in college
and then we lived in Massachusetts again
in the 80s we still go out there
beautiful area I can passionately anyway
as we do Julie do on these currents
episodes we're gonna start with a single
bit in this case a tweet by Joe which
caught my eye and you can probably
imagine why my people who listen to the
show regularly this is what Joe had to
say with no community we lack both a
unit to sacrifice for and a unit to keep
assholes in check what did you mean by
that Joe what did I mean by that well
let's see first I'll say that I don't
vet my own tweets very strongly I'm kind
of a off-the-cuff tweeter I like to just
get my thoughts out there they're not
meant to be refined but I agree in this
case this is that was a in my opinion a
good tweet and so what did I mean by
that so so much of the reflections and
thinking and doing that I've been
involved in the past few years has
revolved around this idea of localism
and we can kind of go into what do I
mean by that what others mean by that
but the essential idea of the tweet is
that biological system
are naturally structured into units at
multiple levels right like so we have
multicellular organisms that are
composed of cells so cells are in some
sense their own stemming uh bounded they
interact with the cells around them but
there's clearly another unit of
organization overlaying the cells that
is the organism that the cells compose
similarly when you let humans do their
natural thing we compose into multiple
layers of units a person can be like a
cell in an organism I say can be because
it's not necessarily the case when we
look at what's happened over the last
where to demarcate I don't know let's
just say last 75 years what's happened
specifically in the US but I think
globally but but I can speak more
directly to the u.s. we've had this kind
of disappearance of what what I'm
referring to as community in that tweet
which is what I take the sort of next
layer on top of maybe not individuals
maybe families too to be so there's sort
of individuals there's families and then
there's a community that's composed of
families I I believe that we are in a
widespread way not universally some
people still have it we have the Amish
and whatnot but in general we are
lacking that community layer of
organization of humans and some of the
consequences of that are that when it
comes time to make tough decisions for
instance think that you know sacrifices
that an individual might make we're
lacking actually a certain not abstract
but concrete unit where we might make
some sacrifices on the individual or
even family level in the interest of
that larger unit and when I say larger
I'm really thinking of something you
know not much bigger than maybe a couple
thousand people maybe it's even smaller
maybe it's more lore Dunbar's number or
something like that you know 150 I don't
know I don't claim to know but I do know
that in the world we exist in right now
the sort of next level up from family to
the extent that we have fam
it's kind of the abstract state often
even conceived of as the national
government or maybe even sort of the
global state systems so so we have this
huge gap between very sort of
small-scale local structures involving
individuals and groups of individuals
and very large-scale abstract
bureaucratic systems that there's no
there's no in-between and then the
assholes in Czech bar had at keeping
assholes in check because those other
organizational units are so far above in
scale of the the local group when an
asshole knows had a game those
bureaucracies say sort of navigate them
in a savvy way that might not be ethical
but jives with the rules of the system
as they stand there's there's no
function there's there's no mechanism
that skins kind of spot that and root it
out or dampen it that's other than the
bureaucracy itself which is which is
simply not close enough not personal
enough not sensitive enough etc to
actually put individual bad action into
place very good I like that a lot
actually ties into some things I've
written an essay I wrote on medium
called a journey to game B I laid out
the thesis that one of the chronic
problems of our time is that what used
to be handled in extended families
that's interesting I have about 65 first
cousins and so if you you know throw in
spouses and a few kids you're around
Dunbar's numbers right and so you know
an extended family used to take care of
business somebody you know went nuts
became a dipsomaniac of a good old
fashioned name for drunk the extended
family took care of one of my uncles had
a problem with the bottle and he lived
in my grandmother's attic for many years
and he wasn't on the street and he
wasn't a nuisance and he was good old
uncle Paul and then the other one was
the extended face-to-face community and
I think you're about right at a couple
of thousand two or three thousand it's
interesting the county
live in Highland County Virginia is the
reputed to be the lowest population
density east of the Mississippi River
and we have about a County about 450
square miles pretty good sized County
2,200 people mm-hmm yep yep thousand
people in my town so yeah I also know
how that feels
yes yeah we don't know I don't know
everybody other 2,200 but I know people
that know everybody so you know what at
noddle distance to I'm connected
everybody in the county s Ashley and
fold out the face to face county a
community so that used to be what took
care of us our extended family around
the Dunbar number plus or minus and then
our face to face community of thousand
to five thousand probably but over time
the extended communities have dissipated
you know my brothers live various places
my cousins are here there and yon right
one lives in Fairbanks Alaska Alaska
another one lives in Utah some of them I
have no idea where they live and the
face to face community has as you
pointed out has seated more and more of
its responsibility to other domains and
the two domains strike me as having
filled that gap is first the government
right as you say some people just think
of the federal government but even if
it's not the federal government it's the
county government or the state
government who are by design as
value-free as we can make them in many
ways right there at least in the United
States and in the Enlightenment model
they should not try to put strong points
of view on things and their definitions
of asshole ish Ness have to be
essentially operational and formal as
opposed to the local the extended family
and the face-to-face community you know
it's like good old Potter Stewart
definition of pornography I know it when
I see it exactly right and so we have
government very formal and then we have
the market which is much more flexible
and accommodating to human nature but on
the other hand it's by definition
anonymous and transactional right nobody
cares about your reputation when you go
in to buy a loaf of bread when it's
money for the dollar and so the things
that used to be happy
handled closer at hand are almost
all now handled either by the government
or the market I've had my choice between
the two I choose the market more often
than not but there are some social
things that need to be done which are
just not being done and you know and I
think you hit on two of them one is
sacrifice you know how many of us are
prepared to sacrifice for the federal
government right not too many people
state of Virginia maybe a little better
as Highland County but for the people of
Highland County yes my face-to-face
community but for the three members of
the Board of Supervisors not really and
how many of us are prepared to sacrifice
for the market not at all like that's
not what markets are for markets are not
for sacrifice therefore you know sort of
anonymous transactions that are mutually
beneficial and that's good that's very
important but it but it doesn't serve
either of your two things the other one
that I thought was interesting that you
hit on but I'm gonna expand and move it
on a little bit our assholes and then
sort of the premium-grade assholes which
are sociopaths right when you have
anonymous situations like markets and
when you have formal systems of levers
of power like government guess who flies
to both of those like like flies to
sociopaths right and to and to my mind
one of the biggest problems of our
society and something we don't fix is
literally going to kill us is the very
high over-representation of sociopaths
in systems of power I have much more
experience on the business side than I
do on the governance side but I say that
at the sea level of real companies
probably 10% of the c-level executives
are sociopaths up from about 1% in in
the general population and if you go
into finance it's probably thirty
percent which is a crazy and scary
thought and that comes from frankly the
transactional nature nature of market
share hoards AAA the stock price up I
don't care if you're a rape and pillage
um sociopath right Lee since
1975 prior
that business actually had included some
community of ethics but I would say
increasingly since 1975 and particularly
for publicly traded companies but also
for larger free public companies
particularly those caught in the vortex
of venture capital sociopathy actually
works what the right and there's
something wrong with that and so you
know moving more of our life back to
scales where you know we actually are
prepared to sacrifice and where there is
some mechanism for keeping assholes in
check strikes me is damn close to of the
essence of how we solve the you know the
meta crisis that our society is in yeah
you know I it's actually interesting
that you sort of define markets as
transactional I definitely agree with
but anonymous that seems to be to me a
consequence of this spreading and
scaling up you know when you repeatedly
went to the same butcher down the street
for 50 years in a row and not only that
but that guy also lives down the other
Street just up the road from you and so
you know him also outside of that
transactional relationship you have
markets that are no longer sort of
decoupled from from that community soil
that community ground and so it's not
merely the transactions that are
actually allowing the markets to the the
goods capital to flow through the market
it's also the relationships that are
layered behind that those transactions
so it's not anonymous and I think that's
part of the problem is that anonymity
where we're looking for these kind of
trustless exchanges and and maybe even
one-off exchanges whereas in a local
setting you get repetitive exchanges you
get different qualities of exchanges I
mean there's obviously currency exchange
there's bartering that becomes more
available because there's not all this
sort of distance friction it's very easy
to you know trade some eggs for some
loaf of bread with your neighbor it's
not it's not a difficult transaction to
facilitate so so I do think that mark
it's in a local context become
non-anonymous
so that I I'm not sure if that's a sort
of a definitional aspect of markets or
if it's sort of an incidental one from
from the current situation we have I
think that's great I love that
distinction you know cuz let's think
about what we do business locally you
know famously in a small town including
this area if you are really in a bad way
they'll extend your credit right and
that's just part of their social
obligation even though they know from an
economic perspective it makes no sense
to lend you money at zero interest that
you may default on right and then of
course the flip side of that is you
better not default if you want your
standing in the community to remain good
then so there's you know there are
non-economic forces as opposed to on
buying something Amazon the only
recourse Amazon has is to you know
sprinkle some powder on my
experience right yeah - anonymous
transactions that are not normal not
what humans are really all about and
then the second one is that when we
react locally in the face-to-face
community we make some interesting
qualitative choices for instance let's
say there's two plumbers in our town
right both of them of similar skill and
similar price but one's an asshole and
the other is a charming person who you
enjoy you know chatting with and you
enjoy having in your home you know if
you make the the principle choice let's
even say the asshole is slightly cheaper
right you make the principal choice that
I'm going to give my business to the
good person
you know that is a non-economic non
anonymous kind of way of doing business
that you know try it as opposed to who
you're gonna buy a can of spam from on
Amazon as you build up your larder for
the zombie apocalypse it doesn't enter
it at all and so that comes to your
other point which is I think at the
broader and extended point which is the
idea around localism as a perhaps better
and more humane way to organize human
human life I know you've thought and
actually you've written quite a bit
about localism you maybe expand on the
on
theme of localism and what that means to
you and why you think it's it's an
improvement over what we have today yeah
absolutely I mean so so much we're
talking about it is in that direction
and I don't think of localism as a
system I kind of think of it as a kind
of meta system it's a structure that
allows multiple systems to emerge sort
of it's similar to the way you can think
of capitalism that way - right the
market is not so much a system as it is
an ecosystem through which various
things evolve and go evolve and whatnot
so III think of localism in a similar
way it's about setting up the conditions
for development and evolution of
particular systems rather than an
imposition of particular systems with
that kind of preamble out of the way I
think what is crucial about local
interaction is what we're talking about
there's necessarily in local
interactions a bundling together of all
of these different flows of flows of
information currency goods and services
and all of the subtle exchanges that we
have as humans that are not easy to
articulate not easy to formalize maybe
impossible in many cases to formalize so
you do you have a interaction with
somebody that maybe is going to do some
plumbing work for something and that's
either an enjoyable interaction or it's
not and that's not something that can be
captured in a dollar value necessarily
so so there's a density of interaction
that we see in the natural world
things that are close together in space
tend to have a high occurrence of
interactions within at one another by
virtue of their closeness to one another
but it's the it's the consequences of
that density of interaction you get
things like emergent like cycles in the
system so you're having loops in the
system you know I'm paying the farmer
down the street for one of his hogs he's
paying the electrician up the road for
their electric work and that electrician
is coming to me and say buying some eggs
off of me and now we're actually having
these circular kinds of flows within the
system that
are in essence nourishing the system and
we're all actually benefiting not only
from the direct transaction the sort of
pairwise transaction that we
participated in but all of the positive
externalities that come out of that
nourishment being local so you know the
the my friends farm down the street is
doing really good business guess what
his property is kept up real nice the
value of the neighborhood is going up so
now his neighbor is also doing better as
his house home value goes up etc etc so
this density of interactions has all of
these sort of emergent effects you can
think of them as side effects but the
important part is that it's not in any
one reducible interaction that the
benefit is it's in the collective
aggregation of all these actions
existing in a dense spot where even
without any planning or explicit
coordination things end up interact in
interacting with one another with a high
density and and circling around the
system and re cycling around the system
in principle you can imagine this
happens at the global scale with global
trade and thing but but there's no
there's nowhere to be to get a handle on
it to get a sense of it things dissipate
more readily and wider systems they
don't necessarily come back around in
any time scale that's meaningful I think
that that the things coming back around
in a short time scale a relatively short
time scale relative to human action
human behavior is a big part of what the
essence of localism offers and again as
we talked about it one of the beauties
is what we while the economic signal is
still there whether it's currency or
barter both are economic both are there
they're wrapped in a broader container
of ethics right ethics and frankly just
su shu ability conformance with decent
behavior and you know you'll wonder why
it actually sort of explains why you
know the quality of human behavior seems
they've been going down for the last 80
years or thereabouts because how most of
our relationships are transactional or
with you know
to mandate identities like the
government right which are supposed to
be gray and bland did not respond
differently whether you're an asshole or
a good person and so of course you know
you do less punishment and less less
punishments of assholes and less
nourishment of good people what do you
expect to get overtime right
unfortunately so I think that's a very
important portal on the other hand let
me throw out the other you know Here I
am in my very remote mountain farm and
population density as low as I mentioned
so we could easily support the
population in the county with our local
agriculture and be able to export quite
a bit and that is a very good feeling
particularly during the mini zombie
apocalypse right we know we're not gonna
starve here under most circumstances but
there was a case back in the I think it
was in the late 30s where this local
small county was hit by a devastating
drought not just a normal drought but a
drought that literally killed everything
right and except for one little corner
of County which now has the name of
little Egypt because most of the people
from the Central Valley had to literally
migrate down to little Egypt with their
cattle pigs chickens and everything else
to just survive that horrendous summer
now I don't think it hit our valley so
bad that over the next Valley over
literally they had to go to little Egypt
and so there is some benefit from expand
you know local clusters that trade with
each other right so if we had and this
was you know when this county I mean we
didn't have electricity here at this
farm till 1962 right so this was a very
remote place in that day but you know
degree it was coupled to you know the
next Valley over and you know up the
river to the next County and down and
over say a you know a four or five
County area you're big enough that you
have differentiated your risks at least
with respect to drought most of the time
and also things like insect pasts and
you know things of that sort so there
you know as we know in investing the
only free run lunch is diversification
there's some of that true also with
respect to
you know to trade so we you know the
idea of becoming ultra local it's you
know autarkic at the level of the county
it's probably a dangerous idea because
it's less robust in some sense then is a
more differentiated portfolio on the
other hand when we get to a very
complicated system like today's world
trade you know we can see instantly what
happens oh all the masks are made
in China the Chinese are holding on to
their mass or right all the nose
swabs in the world are made outside of
Milan Italy or almost all of them who
got hit first by the virus Milan Italy
ups those swabs you know if we'd had a
much more distributed system the
opportunity for robustness in that
system would have been increased so it's
you know you have to think of as a
robustness against various ensembles of
risks and what is the law at the right
level of localism versus essentially a
diversified portfolio so it certainly
feels to me that when you add it all up
we're way to what long range in our
relationships today then would be
optimal and that you know moving these
relationships in so that they're richer
in the face-to-face community and more
personal even the next county over
there's lots of inter marriages people
know each other
there's rest of long-term opportunities
for long-term reciprocity I think would
be a good thing but you know how to do
that is a damn hard question so so I
mean I agree with you on everything you
just said and a lot of times I've
received the feedback on quite a few
occasions where it's sort of hey Joe but
you can't just decentralize everything
to you know whatever down to atoms and
everything's network of course not of
course not but the the take-home message
is that exactly what you said we've gone
so far in the other direction of
centralization of distance
specialisation of things like that that
the movement clearly needs to be in the
local direction and and the ideal is is
and when I say ideal I don't mean the
best state I mean sort of the the thing
that you might aim for sort of as local
as possible but to your point to
mitigate against certain risks to get
other kinds of benefits
as local as possible can sometimes mean
you know the level of the region the
level of the nation so it's it's you
know local is in essence a relational
concept there's no one local what it
means to be local depends on the context
depends on what you're talking about and
and to your point about you know one
County or one area had a drought a
neighboring region didn't and that's the
savior of the neighboring region with
the drought if in that circumstance all
of the agriculture had been concentrated
in the area that happened to receive the
drought everyone would have been screwed
so actually was on a week or so ago Joel
Salatin was on the Joe Rogan podcast and
he articulated very well you know Joe
Rogan asked him how can this scale you
know can it scale and the service of
course it can but it's it's a scaling in
duplication it's not bottle scale or
horizontal scale yeah exactly not not
the sort of vertical integrative growing
monstrosity that people sort of often
naively expect to sort of behave the
same only bigger whereas from system
science we know very well more is
different I I'm sort of adopting bigger
is different language for that because I
think that gets more at the kinds of
things were experiencing directly bigger
is different so you know in that
duplicate of type of growth that
horizontal growth that's where you get
that robustness in that redundancy that
allows you to mitigate against
uncorrelated crises so so for each kind
of possible you know since our ensembles
of risk factors there's a scale at which
these things correlate and then there's
a larger scale at which they don't so
yes absolutely from from a risk
perspective especially we need to be
open to the fact that when in some for
some scale for some area correlated
harmful event occurs disruption occurs
there needs to be support and ability to
exchange with with the next local scale
whatever the neighbors of that unit
happens to be and and and so and so you
know when we talk about localism I often
throw off any qualifier to talk about
local
but really I'm talking about multiscale
localism so you know is a unit the home
and family the town is another unit the
county is another unit the state is
another unit so it's this layering of
units it's not that one needs to take
precedence against all others it's it's
in fact that this distribution across
scales and thinking about that
intelligently is what nobody in power is
doing right it's it's scandalous that if
you were to ask the President of the
United States that you know contemplate
the idea of you know fractal
hierarchical localism you look at you I
who the are you dude right
he'd have not a clue one and how can
that be here in in 2020 when most of our
problems going forward are essentially
complex systems problems that's right
that's right
so I've seen strangely when I've seen
localism the term pop up in a couple
places I haven't been expecting it there
is there does seem to be from this
coronavirus crisis a bit of people's
ears are getting hot when they hear that
because they know they haven't heard it
and they it rings true a lot of people
know there's something about this that's
about right and you're exactly right
that it's not just the politicians it's
our public discourse is mired in this
sort of system verse system you know
communism versus capitalism left versus
right these kinds of is it is that the
right way to administer the system or is
that and all of these conversations are
missing the crucial factor of scale and
for many systems that's going to be
that's going to determine more of the
way the system behaves than the nominal
you know the label of the system that
you're trying to implement so probably a
commune of a thousand people looks more
similar to a small-market of a thousand
people and either of those look to a
market of a billion people or communism
of a billion people yeah I think that's
that's exactly right I do think it's
important for those of us who do see
this to you know keep the discourse
going right in fact I'm actually working
on an essay right now I hope to get it
out in a week or two called it's a call
for a federal Department of wicked wit
risks that would have essentially
informed the federal government
it have a group of people who are
scanning and listening and planning and
modeling etc and doing you know you know
mock decision-making to get leaders
psychologically prepared to make
decisions under stress in complex
situations and you know with this recent
coded things a classic example across
the West
every government essentially failed with
a couple of exceptions Denmark in
Austria maybe New Zealand whose
multi-criteria in Australia a few but
most failed right and so you can't point
to one cloud of misery they all got law
or clouds of misery and if you look back
at who did a better job was mostly
places that had a dry run with SARS
right and so if you could simulate that
in the department of wicked risk say hey
you know what we're gonna have a pan
there pandemics they got knobs of their
contagion or lethality or such here's
our not too implausible and it turned
out to be sorta like koban nineteen
let's run the scenario through and get
the people to think in terms of coupled
complex systems does they think about
that this pandemic has made so clear is
that you know major shocks to the system
aren't just one system this is not just
a health problem right it's a it's an
educational problem it's not gone to
school it's an economic problem at a
massive scale it's a mental health
problem I really read some of the
statistics you know mental health
problems are up by a factor of four or
five perhaps who knows might be
horseshit but we'll soon find out and so
yeah the the need for the public sphere
more broadly you know and not just
government business as well you know
needs to learn how to take a multi
system coupled system multi scale
complex systems view of reality and
start thinking accordingly and if we
don't you know most of the big problems
we have confronting us you know climate
change being a classic one but many
others I don't know how we're gonna
solve them well you know it's
interesting I think that's a necessary
idea to have if we're gonna use these
governing bodies as decision-making
bodies as we are then then setting up a
way of not waiting till the crisis is in
motion to think about how would we
react to this is very important it's not
just the decision-making in the ongoing
crisis though it's also how we structure
our systems and and that's you know for
these systemic risks what makes
something a systemic risk is that there
is that possibility of propagation
either through a single kind of system
you know like the pandemic has on health
you know I get sick I get you sick it's
kind of moving through individuals and
these coupled sort of heterogeneous
Cascades I all of a sudden schools are
closed doors are closing down
meatpacking facilities aren't working so
so much of that needs to be not just the
decisions made in the crisis but the
ongoing decisions we make to structure
the system so that when these things
start to unfold there's boundaries in
the system and circuit breakers and you
know back in January I have a lot of as
many people do criticisms about how
Trump has handled this one criticism I
don't have is his closing of flights
from China in January that was a good
decision and the reason it was such a
politically difficult decision was
because we're not thinking enough in
terms of the structure of the system in
the and the cascades it opens us up to
it should be obvious that if there's a
pandemic risk unfolding somewhere in the
world that's highly connected like China
that it's going to cost us a lot less to
pause flights for a little while than it
is to wait to pause flights pause them
later and also have massive pandemic on
our hands
so these things need to become more
obvious to decision-makers and to how we
govern things it needs to not be just
some esoteric knowledge of some smart
guys in academia or something like that
the other thing about coronavirus it's
interesting connecting back to the the
tweet that we we sort of grounded the
show on I'm pretty sure what I was
thinking about when I wrote that tweet
was the resistance to wearing masks that
were seeing it has become a political
polarization that determines whether
you're for or against wearing masks to
buffer the the spread of a respiratory
disease and it struck me that that's a
small sacrifice throw on a mask to go
into the store that's it's like it's not
a very big sacrifice at all we're not
I'm not saying your livelihood your this
you
that this is like put on a freaking mask
and and you know save someone some real
heartache
maybe someone older maybe maybe one of
your relatives maybe one of your friends
relatives you know if you want to kind
of dice it out into these age groups as
people are doing if we didn't lack that
layer of community I think for most
people regardless of political
disposition that would be a very easy
decision because a community isn't sort
of horizontally partitioned by age
groups or something like that that's
that's a complete artificiality that
we've imposed and we would see the
effects we would say I don't want to
lose these people in my community like
if this is what I need to do small
sacrifice put on a mask you know maybe
someone likes it but I think it's pretty
agreed-upon it's annoying you don't want
to wear it it's but you do it because
it's a small sacrifice that serves the
larger good so that I think that was
actually the source of the tweet it was
both the the fact that there's their
lack of that individual incentive
structure to you know what I'm gonna put
this on because I see how it will affect
my community and I want to help my
community and the assholes that refuse
to do it there's no community to say hey
asshole put on a mask that's
great why don't we wrap it up there
that's the Alpha and Omega this has been
a wonderful conversation Joe just that I
was hoping I figured we'd start with one
place and go every which way which we
did and I think we hate we highlighted
the whole bunch of things that's
worthwhile for people to think about so
thanks for being here absolutely Jim
anytime it's alright very good let me
turn off
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]